Task 32:
We are looking again at IO.
This time we have a C program and a Python
program for the same program written in both C
and Python, and we should
re-implement this in Haskell.
So, as per usual for the IO Task
I've commented out these first lines
to test this locally once
we come up with a solution.
So both of these programs do the same thing.
I will use the Python version since it's
a) closer to where we're working, and
b) I find it a bit more readable.
But, as I said, they both have the same
behavior, and we can choose the one to
work with, or derive our Haskell solution from,
that we are more comfortable with reading.
The program first does something;
defines some x and y variables.
Then it does some looping; this while-loop,
and then prints out the value of y.
This is the basic structure.
In Haskell, we can just start,
let's say, with reading the input.
We can just do x <- readLn.
And then let y = 0, just for the moment.
Then there's something we don't
know how to do, this while-loop.
And finally, we print something, let's say,
y', being the y transformed by this loop.
And that's exactly the notion we need to
adapt in order to implement this in Haskell.
This while-loop; we have to treat it as a
recursive function of type IO something.
As we'll see in a second.
It takes in the current values of x and
y and transforms them into new ones.
So we think of this imperative
while-loop as taking here,
in the beginning, the current values of x
and y, modifying them, iterating over this
thing until this condition
is no longer True, and then
it will return the new values of x and
y for the following program to use.
So we're making this implicit state
of this imperative program explicit.
Okay, let's define a function that does this.
So, as I said, it takes two Integers
and, in principle, it returns the
values of x and y after the loop.
So, we use this now, put in the x and y values,
and then we get out the new x and y values.
We immediately see that we really
don't need this x since it's not
used in this program after the while-loop.
So we can just change the type here
to fit our problem more directly.
Just say, okay, in the end, we
just return the new value of
y and the x value is kept only
for internal use in this loop.
Okay, so we have x and y.
What does this loop do?
Well, it loops until this
condition is no longer true.
That is, if we use guards to do this we
can say x <= 0, then we will return y
because then our loop is finished.
And we return the current value for y that we
kept as the state and will be passing around.
Okay, so the next condition then is if this
is actually true we go into the loop body.
And then we check if this condition holds,
so x `mod` 2 == 0, then we do something.
And we also need an otherwise case which is
kind of the else branch here, but we have to keep
in mind that this print is always executed after
one iteration of the loop, no matter
what the branching condition was.
So we can just say there's a 'print'
in here somewhere at the end,
but we're also not sure
what to print at the moment.
So, let's see, we need to compute
the new values for x and y.
And do any IO actions that
we need to do in this branch.
So the new value for x is just x
divided by 3 without any floating-point
stuff, just plain old whole number division.
So, let's say we use a let statement
and say, okay, the new value of x,
call it x', is the old value of x,
which is our input here, divided by 3.
And then, before we continue with the next
loop iteration, we have to print the current
value of x, which is now the new value,
obviously, because we updated it here.
It's not the input anymore, so we print x'.
And now we have to initiate the next
iteration of the loop with the new values
which is the new x' and y didn't change.
Okay, let's do the same thing
for the else branch here.
The first thing we do is we read in
a new value for x, so x' here is
this IO action reading in from the command line.
Then we say, the new y is
the old y + 1, and again we print the current
value of x, which is the one we just read in.
And then we do the next loop
iteration; so x' and y'. Okay.
And since we use this y' we defined
here just once, we can just simply
put it here without duplicating any
subexpressions, and it gets a little
easier to read.
We can obviously do the
same with our y = 0 up here
which we just used in the beginning
to sketch out the program.
Okay, now let's load this up
in ghci and see what happens.
Okay, so simple input: if we choose
0 we don't execute the loop at all
so we immediately return the
current value of y which is 0.
Okay, let's do a bit more complicated
thing, let's say we start with 2.
It's not that more complicated for the interaction
because we're just going here in the first
branch dividing 2 by 3 which results in 0, so 2
`div` 3 is 0, and then the loop terminates and
we have printed out
0 one time because that's the
new x that we print here.
Let's say we start with 3.
Then we get into this part here where we just
now are asked to provide an additional number.
Let's choose 1; 1 is printed out.
1 is still not divisible by 2
so we're again at this point.
Let's choose 2 again to
terminate in the next iteration.
The current value of x that we
just read in is printed out.
Then this division is computed again.
The result is printed out here and then the
condition is false and we exit the loop.
And since we read in 2 values at this point
y has a value of 2 which is printed out here.
Okay, so this seems to work, and submitting
this solution to Autotool will do more rigorous
checking but then it will also just tell you
that this program has the correct behavior,
as far as these tests go.
And by looking at it you can
really see that it should have.
Of course, there are many different
ways you can write the same behavior.
You don't have to use guards here.
You can use if-then-else, and the if-then-else
branching structure is more similar to this one.
Then you might not have to
duplicate this print action.
But the basic concept that you have this
loop function which keeps track of the
current values, and in the end returns
the final values will be present in all
solutions because we don't have these stateful
updates we have in imperative programs.